这期教程中 我们将介绍如何
For this tutorial, we're gonna cover how to
创建单维材质
create a single material
和带有子材质的多维材质
and a multi-material with sub-materials inside the material editor.
以及在材质之间复制属性值
We're also show how to copy and paste values between one another,
这样可以快速设置好你想要的材质
so then you actually get the settings you want quicker
而不必去输入每一项属性
without having to go in and manually input every single thing.
若要进入材质编辑器
So, to go to the material editor,
选择Tools下的Material Editor
we can go to Tools->Material Editor,
把它固定在这边
we're gonna go ahead and dock that over to the right here.
把面板拉大点
Let's go ahead and expand this out.
接下来我们要
And what we wanna do is we want to actually
获取选中的素材 点这个按钮
get the properties from the selection, so it's this button.
会看见选中的是wood_beams_burnt
We'll see it immediately that this is wood_beams_burnt,
展开它
if we scroll that out,
有了这个材质后 我们想要
we now have a material and what we wanna do
复制这个材质
is we want to copy a material
到一个新创建的材质中
into another material that we're gonna create.
本期中我们要创建2种材质
We're gonna create 2 types of materials here,
我要创建跟这个一模一样的材质
we're going to create an identical one just like this.
要这样做的话
So if I were to do that,
点击右键 选择Duplicate
I can right click and I can do duplicate,
现在便有了wood_beams_burnt1
so now I have wood_beams_burnt1,
然后
and
我还可以自定义一个
I can also do it where I can only do
我想要的多维材质
a multi-material that I explained, that I want.
这个材质里有6个通道
In this one, I have 6 channels.
若是我只想有4个通道呢
Well, what if I only want to have 4?
要想创建 回到上面shaderball文件夹
In order to do that, I can go up to shaderball,
选择添加新的多维材质
and I can say Add New Multi Material.
选择wood_beams_burnt
So if I were to click in here, let's do wood_beams_burnt,
文件名添加TUTORIAL 以便区分
we will do TUTORIAL, just so we know it,
然后保存材质
and we'll save,
然后右键 便可设置子材质数量
then we can right click and we can set the number of materials.
我设置成4
So now I have 4.
我便有了4个材质在里面
So now I have 4 materials in here,
但材质名是自动生成的
but they're randomly named,
不能顾名思义
and they're also not containing any of the information I want.
所以我右键
So I can right click on this,
重命名子材质
and I can rename that sub-material.
命名成跟原来第一个子材质一样的名称
Let's rename it to the same thing as the first one which is the proxy,
也就是proxy_SUB
so proxy_SUB.
现在有了proxy_SUB
So now we have proxy_SUB,
其他也同样重命名
and we can rename some of these as well
outside
to outside
outside_SUB
to outside_SUB
同样的重命名为ce_Logo
and then we're also do ce_Logo,
最后一个我们自己命个名 命名为
and then the last one we'll make a custom one, and we'll name this one
collin_SUB
collin_SUB.
那么这个代理材质
So the proxy material,
我把这个
if I were to
拉开点
expand this out,
进入wood_beams_burnt的代理材质的属性
I can go ahead and go to the proxy one underneath the wood_beams_burnt,
右键 复制所有
and I can right click and select copy all.
回到我们创建的代理材质
So if I want to do that, I go to copy all
然后粘贴
and then paste all, same kind of thing.
这个材质便继承了不渲染着色器和外表类型
So now you'll see we've inherited the nodraw shader and surface type
到第一通道里
into our first channel.
接下来我们进outside
The next thing that we can do is we can go to outside,
以同样的方式复制 观察变化
let's do the same thing, just so we can see it change.
可以看见它自动的复制了整个子材质
And you'll see that we automatically just took that entire sub-material.
若我只想复制一个类别呢
What happens if I wanna just copy a category?
在灯光设置中 右键 Copy Category
So in the lighting settings, I can copy the category,
回到ce开头的材质
I can come back to the ce profile,
然后粘贴 可以看见它只复制了灯光设置
and if I paste that, you'll notice that it only did the actual category.
这可以让你选择性复制
So this gives you a chance to actually pick and choose
灯光设置 而不会覆盖整个材质所有属性
based on just the lighting settings but not actually overriding the whole material
或子材质自身
or sub-material itself.
以及 最后 我可以再次
And the last thing that I can do is I can just once again
复制 粘贴
copy all and paste.
在继续之前
Before we move on,
我想向你展示下wood_beams_burnt
I want to actually show you wood_beams_burnt.
这里我们有wood_beams_burnt
So in this, we have wood_beams_burnt,
我们能复制它
and we were able to duplicate it.
如果我想复制整个材质和子材质
What if I wanna duplicate the entire material and sub-materials
还不用逐个进去复制呢
without having to go in each one?
刚才的方法是逐个进去复制子材质
Because otherwise, what we've shown is we just done each sub-material.
现在我们进入到soil
So let's go in the soil,
我们要做的是复制soil_b
what we can do is we can copy soil_b,
然后进入wood_beams_burnt1
and we can go into wood_beams_burnt1.
在此处粘贴
Let's go ahead and paste this,
然后点取消即可
and just press cancel.
现在再看
Now if we go into it,
会发现所有子材质都已替换成了
you'll notice that all the sub-materials have actually taken on
soil材质 而且无需逐个
the soil material without actually having to go in
复制粘贴每个子材质
and copy and paste each individual sub-material.
目前为止 我们已经定义了所有子材质
Since we've gone in there, we've explained all the sub-materials,
最后最简单的内容 我们可以添加新材质
so let's keep the easiest for last and that is we can add a new material,
我们将其命名为tutorialSINGLE
and we can call this one tutorialSINGLE,
然后它会在文件夹中添加一个简单的子材质
and it'll just add a simple sub-material in theory,
也没有父材质
and not have a master material.
然后我们进到这里 复制所有
And then we can go in here, we can copy all
然后粘贴
and then we can paste.
所以这期教程快速概览了
So this has given you a quick overview on how you can
如何通过复制和粘贴
pretty much manipulate materials
来管理材质
through copying and pasting it,
创建单维或多维材质
making single and multi-materials,
以快速装扮你的场景
to able to dress up your scene quickly,
并使用GameSDK中的内容
and manipulate things that may already exist in GameSDK,
或者是同事做好的材质
or from your teammates on your own development.
翻译：他出院了